[music]
Hi. Uh, I'm Bill Maxwell. As Patrick
said, I will be going over how to build
NextG agents uh with MCP.
And so we'll just kind of set some
context with what MCP is, how to use it,
what are and how it kind of works. And
then we will get into building our own
agent that will end up playing chess
with us. Um, and we'll be starting with
a textbased game and moving our way to a
graphical one where you can interact
with um the agent through uh a graphical
chessboard.
So I'm not going to go super in depth on
what MCP is. Tomorrow I'm giving another
talk on the guts of MCP. But for the
purpose of this uh workshop, we're going
to go with uh MCP servers are
essentially like USBC ports for
application AI applications. So being
able to plug in systems into models and
making that easy to uh consume. They're
portable between models and systems. So
any of your clients that support MCP um
will be able to use those tools and have
those capabilities.
Um, they connect in two primary methods.
You've probably seen uh JSON snippets
that have either like a npx or uvx when
running your MCP server. That's
typically running at local and it'll be
communicating over standard IO. And in
that case, you know, it's just basically
a local process and your client is
passing messages directly to um uh the
MCP server. And that was sort of the way
it started out uh and where it
originated from. And it's evolved uh to
streamable HTTP. So now you can have uh
centralized hosted MCP servers that your
clients can connect to um uh remotely
and they you know or also as a third
party if you want to provide an MCP
server to your customers and users um
your systems uh you can also build and
host and platform or manage it that way.
Uh, previously they attempted to do the
remote bits over uh, SSE. Um, you'll
still possibly see a few of those around
just because all of the indexes get
scraped and they're [snorts] really not
going for quality just yet. Um, so you
might run across a few of the older uh,
SSE based servers.
On a server side, uh an MCP server, the
core thing I think everyone thinks of
when they think of MCP servers is tools.
And basically that is the actions that
uh the agent and the client are going to
be able to take and interact with those
systems. And so basically with these uh
you know you can get records, get um you
know change a database, query a
database, uh call an API, any of those
um are pretty common pieces. The other
bits are more around some of the UX and
the data that might be interacted with.
So prompts guide the user uh and how to
interact with that server. uh resources
are files or URLs to data or records in
a database uh that need to be referenced
um and so the server can present those
uh to the client.
Uh the reason I bring some of these up
is tools and resources are going to be
pretty core to uh what we end up
building today. Um so those are some
important concepts.
The others that are on the client side
uh are sampling, which is a weird name
and they'll admit it. Uh but basically
it is the server requesting the client
to make an LLM call. So if you've pulled
some text, you can ask the LLM the
client to summarize those that text for
you, have it go back to the tool, get
processed and sent back. Elicitations
are a pretty vital part. Uh those come
back and confirm actions from the user.
So the user can either, you know,
confirm or deny an action or did you
really mean to deposit a million
dollars, you know, like confirm that the
data and the information is correct? And
then roots, um, I don't really think
anyone uses those, but basically they
just tell you where in the file system,
uh, tells the server where in the file
system they can interact with things.
So let's get to the fun part uh where we
actually build and uh do the code. Um
you will need an open AI key. Uh if you
go to this URL, you will go to a word
doc or a Google doc that will have an
API key that you can use for this if you
don't want to use your own. Um
so yep if you visit this it will take
you to
this document where you can get the key.
I previously tried this with a QR code
and then it ended up on everyone's
phone. So I'm hoping just the URL this
time.
So I put this on the next slide. Um, for
those of you who have the key, the next
bit is to install Nanobot. So, we're
going to be using Nanobot for this. It
is an open source project by Obot. It is
uh like a lightweight agent framework um
that uh basically is a full MCP client
implements all of the the bits. It
allows you to define an agent which
we'll go with as a model, instructions,
and tools. The tools will be provided by
the MCP server. Um and we'll be using
nanobots. So we'll go into a little bit
more on that. So if you're going to
build you will need uh nanobot.
Okay.
And then last you will want to clone
this repository.
Um, and this will have everything we
need to set up the
uh uh agent today.
[snorts]
while we wait for everyone. Yep.
>> Yep.
Do you need this one or the pre? Okay.
>> Sorry. Yeah. Please stop me if I'm going
too fast or
you have questions, please ask. Uh,
happy to
Okay. Is everyone been able to install
Nanobot
and clone the repo.
Then we need help.
Okay.
Okay. So, I'm going to work out of this
uh here for the most part going through
the uh the repository. If you go into
your the chess MCP directory, you'll see
there is a workshop and a workshop live
folder. You'll want to go into that
folder um as we work through this.
And um
that'll be the primary. If you get lost
or get stuck, the solutions are in the
solutions folder and the readme and
these slides that I'll be working off of
uh exist in both the
I am going to cheat a little bit and
just give you I am going to have the
readme open in another folder um because
I don't want to type everything.
Okay, so we are going to build a fully
functioning uh chess MCP server. Uh it
will have a backend. You'll be able
it'll have some tools uh to be able to
make a move. It will uh be able to, you
know, have the rules enforced. Um and
you'll be able to actually play chess.
Um
so it accepts the algebraic notation
which is you knight to E4 and that type
of thing. I personally am not super
wellversed in it and have to often ask
uh what I mean when I from the model and
have it tell me. Um but then this will
have state. It will have a way to
display the board and then we're going
to take a moment and go over like uh MCP
UI and then we will implement the UI
elements for this agent and then you can
drag and drop and play chess.
Um
yeah. So you will need NodeJS. Uh you'll
need some basic uh TypeScript. Um your
editor of choice. I'm going to use VS
Code. Uh command line. You'll need two.
One to run the uh server and one to run
uh the nanobot instance.
And we've already cloned.
And now, so in the workshop live folder,
you're going to want to install our npm
dependencies.
Um, what we're going to be installing is
we're going to be using MCPUI server.
We're just going to install that now.
We're going to use the official SDK from
the model context protocol. Uh, we're
going to use chest.js, JS which is the
backend for the chess engine and then
express and zod for um
uh
types.
Okay.
Got held them myself.
All right.
So now we're going to create our minimal
uh MCP server. Um we're going to be
adding we're going to look at the basic
structure of the server. We're going to
register our first tool. Uh we're going
to fire up um we're going to set up the
transport layer. And then we are going
to um yeah have our first tool and test
that out with Nanobot. And so our first
goal is to uh create the serverts file.
And you will find that in source lib
serverts. You should see it empty uh
with that. And like I said, I'm going to
cheat
and copy this
and I will walk through it.
Y zoom in a little bit
just
>> Oh yeah.
[clears throat]
Okay.
So, in this file, we're going to add our
imports. Uh, we're going to do add
express. We're going to add our
middleware. Um, we're going to pull in
the MCP server from the SDK. And then
we're going to use ZOD.
So, here, can everyone see this? Is this
a good size? Good. Thank you. Um, we're
going to create our new server. Um, in
this function here,
um,
we're basically just giving it a sample
name and a version.
So then once we've created our server,
we're going to register our tool.
This one is going to just add numbers.
So for this one, we're just going to
keep it nice and simple. Um, we're going
to define our tool and give it a a
description and its input schema. This
is going to take the left and right
operand of an add function. Um,
and so here you can see we're using ZOD
to describe that it's numbers and then
give it these uh descriptions so that
the model can view these things. Your
tool names and your descriptions, your
tool name probably is most important
followed by the description of each of
these when building your MCP servers if
you want to have success. um you'll want
to make sure that those are very
descriptive and accurate so that the
model doesn't really guess.
Then [sighs]
we're going to create the actual body of
the tool. And so here
we are going to return content
of type text
and basically just say the sum of the
left and right is the left and right.
And we'll close that out and then return
the server.
Just make sure you can see the whole
function.
And then we will wire up Express. And so
we'll mount it to SLMCP which is the
convention of
U MCP servers that are over streamable
HTTP. We'll log and we will listen on
port 3000.
Sorry.
Okay,
sorry. Was everyone able to get this? If
you fall behind the again the solutions,
if you want to look at the files, they
are in the steps. So, we're on step one.
You can also see it in here. I'm going
to actually copy out the nanobot yaml
because it's currently in the form for a
later version.
So you want to edit your nanobot yaml to
look more like this for this particular
part. And so just kind of breaking down
our nanoboty file. Uh this is basically
as we were saying earlier this is our
agent. It's really quite simple. Um it
is just a model, some instructions and
some tools. And those tools
um are basically just provided by the
MCP server that we've just built. Um,
we're going to use GPT41
and we're just going to give it some
simple um
simple instructions to basically use the
tool that it has access to.
All right.
So, if everyone's okay, anyone need more
time? I'm going to start the MCP server.
I'm going to just do npm rundev.
So, now we've started the MCP server. We
basic because when we set up our express
app we're listening on port 3000MCP
and so now we are up and running and now
uh
we have our nanobotl file. So I'm also
in this live folder and I'm going to do
npm or sorry nanobot.
Oh, sorry. I'm skipping a step here.
Before you run nanobot in your terminal,
uh export that open AI uh yeah, open AI
key um through this environment
variable.
So, if you copy what I put in the um
document, that uh should just work.
[clears throat]
So,
So basically what's going to happen is
when nanobot starts it looks for that
environment variable then it has an API
key to talk to uh openai.
So then we will run nanobot
run nanobot yaml file and you'll see
that you should see that it starts up
and that it comes and starts listening
on port 8080.
So then if you go to your browser, you
should see a nanobot
UI.
Does everyone Is this working? Not
working? Anyone need help?
All right. Now you should be able to
just chat with it. So now I should be
able to say uh add, you know, 9 + 8. And
you should see that it'll run and it
knows to use its uh tool. So it's
calling our MCP server and it is adding
uh basically it gets the output in the
format that we said it should and
returns
the correct answer.
Anyone not seeing this or hitting some
errors? Need any
any help? Yep.
the export and then just getting
>> Is that in the same
Is it in the same folder?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, that one. Are you in the live
folder?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Live.
>> Yeah. So, it needs to should run that
one.
>> It cheats.
>> It does.
>> Yeah.
Look, look, look here. Wait, let me show
you.
>> I was I put my queen here and then he
said he captured with this pawn. I'm
like, that's an illegal move down.
>> So, he did an illegal move and then cuz
I made him think the board and then I
came back here and I'm like, that's not
a valid move, you cheater. [laughter]
>> And then and then he wrote back like,
oh, right. He put the piece back.
>> Huh?
>> You should say,
>> well, you tried to cheat.
>> You should say. [laughter]
>> All right. So, if you run it with slash,
what does it do?
Yeah, try that. There you go.
>> What directory do we refer to inside the
nanobot runtime? Because it says that
the file is not found, but it is
>> kind of cool.
>> Yeah. Um,
>> sorry. I'll be right back.
So you should be in the working
directory. So you're in working
directory.
>> Y
>> and uh let me just run this.
>> Delete that.
>> Dude space dot
>> queen to
>> Yep. Try that.
It's not available.
>> See how you installed that? How you
install nanomot?
>> Uh, I used group.
>> Did you use the full rule cask?
>> Right.
>> Okay.
>> That's amazing.
>> Should I install it again?
>> Just take over. Just take over the
>> That's amazing.
Let me go check one thing real quick.
So
>> [laughter]
>> kind of
Was it moving my Look, I'm moving my P.
You should do one more
>> possibly, but it looks like it's got
some sort of validation error.
E5 to E7.
>> Demo.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Do you have
>> [clears throat]
>> Okay, that's up.
>> Oh, he put his knight there.
>> The dev servers do not restart
automatically, do they?
>> They do not. No.
>> Okay, maybe I'll just try restarting
because I just changed the name of the
server. It was a mismatch. So,
>> yeah. So these two have to match and
then
>> it's not just
>> like it is silly but it's example how
gaming might look in the future
>> like a kid will just be like
[clears throat]
>> this is how the game's going to work
today
>> and it's just like
>> on the fly they'll be able to play games
the way they want to
>> that's okay
>> can you copy the nanobot yl out of step
one and just copy the file directly
there and try that
>> you can cheat really
>> I That's how you started nanobot.
>> Oh, it is uh you export the openi a kpi
key and in the same terminal it is
nanobot run
>> space
nanobot.yamlot.
>> Cool.
>> You are
>> Did that help?
>> No. No.
>> What do we expect in schema?
>> Uh I don't it's I'm guessing it's like a
validation thing. It doesn't seem to
like
>> which nanobayl file is this?
>> Uh it's this one. I just copy the
content from
>> you think it's
>> okay.
>> Yeah. And that should be
>> main test. Okay.
>> Yeah. This really shouldn't.
>> Can you brew uninstall it?
>> Oh, uninstall.
>> Yeah. And then
>> because there's a a version there's a
brew install nanobot and then that one
is broken.
>> Oh,
>> so there's one with the Yeah, let me put
it back up on the screen for you.
>> [sighs]
>> So, if you're seeing an error when you
install Nanobot, if you did brew install
Nanobot without putting the Nanobot AI
tap, uh, that version is broken. We're
still working with Upstream to actually
get that fixed. So, if you could brew
uninstall the nanobot that way and brew
install this nanobot, hopefully that
fixes the issue.
Okay.
>> You're supposed to install the tap,
right? Tap.
>> Yeah, you're supposed to install the
tab.
>> I was supposed to install the tap.
>> Yeah. Oh, okay. That's what happened.
Never mind.
>> Okay.
>> This is what we get
request.
>> Did you
>> I ran the server here. Did npmi?
>> Yep.
>> Uh server ts files. We looked at the
solutions for step one looks the same.
The file identifies look the same.
>> Sure.
>> And then is there anything else we're
supposed to do?
>> API.
>> Yep. That should be good. And then here
you're getting
>> Oh, you want to start the nanobot server
and hit it on 8080. You're
[clears throat] not speaking MCP when
you go to it in the URL in the browser.
>> Okay.
Uh
>> what do I need to do?
>> Go to 80 uh port 8080, not 3000.
Uh, did you start the nanobot process?
>> I don't think so. I think that's the
missing part.
>> Yep. You need to start nanobot and then
that will listen on that.
>> And really quickly, I've got the the yo
here and I try to start nanobot in live.
Is that the right folder to start it in?
>> Yes, it's in live. Oh, the nanobot yl
should be out here.
>> So, this one is already there, right?
>> Yeah. Overwrite that one.
>> Overwrite that one with this one. Okay.
And how do you start?
>> And then nanobot.
>> No nanobots in live.
>> Yeah, it should be the live folder. So
then do nanobot
>> uh space run
dot slash dot forward slash
>> forward this one.
>> Uh dot forward slash
>> uh nanoboty.
There you go.
>> Spaced. Cool.
>> Awesome.
>> Now you should be on 8080
>> brother.
>> Hey, don't worry. It's like trying to
find the Docker file.
>> Oh, did you export your Open AI key in
that?
>> Oh, not in this one.
>> Yeah, you're gonna need that.
>> Oh, I didn't do that either.
>> Okay, you're gonna need that.
>> Okay, but I can do that without that.
>> There we go.
>> Cool. Now, you should be able to ask it.
>> Huh?
You're running it in a folder above the
live workshop live.
>> Okay.
>> You're running
one down here. Okay, doors. Thanks.
>> Okay, so you guys are good.
>> Oops. Sorry.
>> Yeah, I will not do that twice.
All right.
Were you able to Nope.
Okay. I'm sorry. I will look at this
with you.
>> Not a problem.
>> Okay. Thanks.
All right.
So, I know a few of you have this up and
running. Um,
so hopefully you've had fun adding
numbers.
Let's make it do more interesting
things.
So, just to recap though, what we've
done though is we have created the MCP
server. We added the tool for adding and
basically the middleware layer. Um the
reason we're using the middleware layer
helps us run both MCP and standard HTTP
over the thing uh the same proto same
port and we are getting our responses
back.
So now let's get into the chess side of
things which is the more fun and
interesting bits.
And so here what we'll do is we'll use
the chessjs library. Um we'll implement
uh uh the chess tools that we'll need
for this and then it handles the
validation and then we will add uh game
state. It will return the formatted game
state.
So chessjs is an open uh is a library
that's out there. Uh we've already
installed it. Um it has the complete
rules. It's a pretty cool backend. Um so
we'll get asy board rendering. Um, it
helps validate the moves apparently not
very well. Um, and then it manages the
uh game state for us.
So now let's edit our
uh server. We're going to delete the
tool here.
and we will add the new tool.
So you know first we will
add our import
for chest.js JS.
Uh, we'll have the new chess.
We are going to We still have our same
server. That part's still good. Uh,
we're going to register our new uh tool
called the
um
chess move.
it'll take the move um as a parameter.
[clears throat]
And then when we actually go to do the
move, we'll create a a new chess object.
We will do the move and then we will
return the state.
Okay.
So, I'm going to save that.
I'm going to kill my MCP server. I kill
Nanobot and bring them back up.
So, here's my new
uh MCP server. It's started back up. And
then I will run Nanobot. I'll use the
same uh Nanobot file that we had from
before.
And
When I reload,
start a new chat. I'm just going to say
E4.
So, it now knows
to call the chess move.
And you can see that it is now um
returning the response as we told it to
in our file. So here we're still telling
it that our response is going to be a
text. It's going to have the current
board state. Um this just dumps it in
that notation. Um it gives a list of
valid moves and then it gives the ASKI
format of the
uh game state.
And you'll note if you do
so if you say E5, it'll make the chess
move again.
But
um yeah, you'll notice that it's
actually not keeping state and you get a
new board every time in this particular
step.
Has everyone had a chance to get it to
the point where it's now running this
first step? Uh
>> I was uh I didn't get the ask to show up
>> in the
showing type show.
>> You're running the complete final
solution. This version will only have
the move tool.
>> Oh,
>> yeah.
>> Are you running? Where are you running
your nanobot file from?
I was running it from
>> I took the one that was there and
uncommented.
>> Are you in is your terminal in the live
folder?
>> Yes.
>> No,
server.
>> Yeah, it's in the workshop live.
>> Okay. And then is your MCP server
running out of
>> which will
>> Yeah, I took the I took the
server code from the reunion.
>> Yeah.
>> For step two.
>> Okay.
>> And it's it seemed to be persistent
state
>> and that was after you made your first
chess move. It's
>> it's probably the model remembering
where which state
>> [clears throat]
>> That can't be
I tried to do um installing but then
somehow this is impossible. Xcode is
fine. I can open it.
>> Do you have the
>> I mean it's up and running. It's right
here. I'm downloading simulators, but
it's the latest version.
>> Do you have the Xcode and CLI tools?
>> Oh, yeah.
Build
I did hyphen version and it's the latest
app store.
>> It's either outdated or was modified.
Please update your Xcode or delete it if
there are no updates available.
>> Are you on 15?
>> Yeah.
>> Seems weird.
>> I know, right? Everything's like pretty
much the latest
>> Sequoia 156.
>> Yeah,
>> but your Xcode is the 261.
>> Yeah, that's that's the latest in the
app store. I already double check. It's
not like a like a you know developer
version or anything.
>> No, no,
just [clears throat] kind of like
stalled.
I'll just have to pile on later.
>> I'm sorry.
>> That's weird. I
>> never seen that before. I try restarting
the terminal too. The session is gonna
be a good reboot.
>> Maybe um we'll let you do like a brew
update and brew upgrade brew.
>> Uh not for Xcode, but maybe it's brew
trying to use something in its area. I
don't know what's actually throwing the
error.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Okay.
I'm pretty sure that basically the board
and what the model think are existing
are not coinciding. So when it shows the
board, it shows the white move, but
black can't move because it goes to
move, but white needs to go first.
At least that's what's happening on
mine.
Okay. So [sighs]
now let's add state um so that we can
actually
get kind of going back and forth.
So I'm going to kill those.
So we're going to we did that played a
little chess. So each request generates
a new game. So basically there is no
state persisted although the model is
smart enough to remember that it got a
tool call response and the state of the
board. So it's just kind of holding on
to that and it won't let it go.
So [sighs] again we can now see the
board. We're actually able to make the
moves. We're calling our tool. The
backend is kicking in.
And so now what we're going to want to
do is actually have state management so
we can survive multiple turns.
And so here we're just going to use a
simple uh session state based on the
session ID. So every time you connect to
the MCP server, you are generating a
session ID. um we're going to store that
use that to store um on the file system
the state of the game and then we will
load that before every move for that
session and then we will be able to play
and continue.
So now we're going to create a new file
in our lib directory
uh store.ts TS.
And so here we're just bringing in write
file, read file, and make dur um
see if it exists. and the chess game.
So, we're going to bring in the backend
from chess
and we're going to create a save game
function. We're going to take the
session ID from the MCP server. Um,
we're going to take the game from chess
and the chess back end. We're going to
check if it uh exists. If it doesn't,
we're going to make a games uh directory
with there. And then we're going to
write the JSON file um with our session
ID and stringify the uh the game. So
then it's just going to dump it uh to
file.
Then we're going to write the flip side
and we're going to do the load game. And
so it will also take the session ID. Um
it will then read the games folder for
that JSON file. And if it exists, it
will return that data
as a JSON or as a chess object with the
um with that data.
So now we'll update our server.
And so here,
instead of creating a new game every
time,
we'll let game equal await
load.
So we'll bring in our load game and
save game.
And then we'll say
if move
So here we're checking to see if it's a
new move or
if there's no game coming back from the
uh from our load game state. And then we
are going to make the move and
immediately after we are going to save
our game. after we make that move
[snorts]
and we are going to continue returning
the same content that we've returned
before
and now we should see it persist state
and we should be able to make multiple
moves.
So we will fire up the MCP server and
then we will fire up Nanobot,
[clears throat]
start a new chat.
Okay, so here now in theory I should be
able to say E5.
Cool. And so now if you look at our ASI
or I can say showboard,
you can see both pieces have moved and
black was actually able to go because it
was Black's term according to the back
end. The nice thing about when you're
building these MCP servers is all your
business logic can go into the MCP
server and that way you're not really
relying on the model and its guard rails
to uh um make the right choices or
decisions. So here you get a bit more
security by embedding your business
logic into the tools into the backend
MCP server. Um and then you're able to
actually,
you know, build reliable uh systems.
Cool. Was everyone able to get their MCP
server to save this state? And if we go
back and look, we should see that our
games are now being stored in our um by
session in our folder here.
And here why don't we also enhance our
uh nano nanobot eml file. We'll go back
to the fancy one.
So that will improve this gives you some
um
some nice things here. So I'll go over
that.
So, we can say, "Let's play a game of
chess. I'll go first. Whoever goes first
is
uh
is typically the the white color pieces
and
um it'll be able to actually execute and
get going." Oh, no. This one's too
fancy. We're going to use step threes.
Sorry about that.
So here what we're doing is just adding
a little bit of niceness. Um so we're
adding some starter messages. So when
you load your agent typically in a chat
window you're just presented with a
chat. And so that's what you type. Uh so
with starter messages, we're able to
give it um
basically a nice UI button that lets you
click and kick off the conversation and
then you'll be able to um enhance the UX
a bit. So here
when I create a new one. So here now
it's got the uh chest piece logo. And
now you've got some starter buttons. So
you can say let's play. I'll go first.
And so then I can say I'm going to be
move to E4.
And now it automatically knew and picked
up and started playing. And so the game,
the agent is now actually starting to
play back and forth with you. And so if
you know chess notation, uh you can keep
playing. I know E4 moves it. And then I
I think I've memorized now that knight
can move to
knight to E F3.
So that will move.
If I look at the board.
So here now we're looking at this and
you have a way to actually play chess
with an agent and go back and forth. The
downside to this at the moment is we're
chatting and we have to do everything in
text and in this case text is not great,
right? Like you have to kind of know
this notation. I mean, I guess if you
already knew it, it wouldn't be so bad,
but it's not visual. It's not really
easy way to think through it. It's not
super like it's just bad UX.
And I think you know where chat sort of
falls down a little bit.
So,
let's bring up MCP UI.
So, MTP UI, this is what's going to this
helps us um we'll be using this to add
interactive UI elements to the chess
game. And so, this will allow us to
basically ultimately have a drag and
drop way to interact with it. So,
real quick, um, not real quick, but so
MCPUI is a project by a team out of
Shopify. Um, I don't know if you're
aware of this, but every Shopify account
has its orfront has its own MCP server.
And one of the things they wanted to be
able to do was be able to, you know,
still have that interactive chat
experience while still being able to
shop. So if you go to the with a client
that supports MCP UI, if you go to the
Shopify MCP stores like All Birds or
something like that, you can actually
get like and say you're shopping for
shoes, it will, you know, pull up a
catalog of shoes. It'll let you click
through the carousels. It gives you a
way to completely interact with and
still kind of have that visual
experience that you kind of want when
you're buying something like shoes or
clothing or any number of things. You
kind of want to see it, right? And so
that's one of the nice things um
about uh
yeah having a UI um and so
yeah they they wanted to be able to do
that and so from that you can also add
things to cart and then you have to go
and actually complete the cart
experience out there but what is nice
about sort of the chat pieces or what
it's bringing is you can say I'm
shopping for shoes and you don't have to
worry about the navigation of going to a
website entering into a search bar
clicking on you know men's shoes, then
sneakers, then all these things, right?
If you think about half the things that
you're doing on a website when you're
building it or looking at it, um you're
basically thinking through the
navigation and how do I find something,
right? Like that's where you spend most
of your time. How do I get my users from
A to B? Chat is really nice because it
cuts out a lot of that and what it um
what you need to do there. And so the
MCP UI guys, they actually uh saw MCP,
they really like the protocol and they
figured out how to build on top of it
and extend um which makes it nice as a
protocol. So what they've done is
uh figured out a way to build rich
interactive UI experiences on top of uh
MCP.
And so by doing it this way, they've
standardized uh the way of like the
client server side things uh as far as
like SDKs and being able to define
specific interfaces and how you can
communicate back and forth. Um they've
done it in a secure way. So when you
render it on the client side, it is
sandboxed in an iframe and so you're
able to, you know, trust the code to
some degree there that's running in
there. Um, it's interactive, so you can
click within the UI or you can chat and
have it do things in the UI as well. So,
it can go both ways, which is pretty
cool. Um, it's uh flexible in that it
can embed or have raw content and then
it's, you know, they're just extending
and so they're doing it in a way that
doesn't back anyone or paint anyone in
any corners. Um, I believe
uh the OpenAI
uh apps SDK, I think that's the new one
they released, is actually a smaller
subset of some of the capabilities that
you can do with um MCP UI.
And so on the server side,
[clears throat] excuse me, um you're
basically in your MCP server, you're
rendering UI resources. um these write
on top of just regular MCP type
resources. Um and then they're also
making use of the spec where a tool call
can return an embedded resource. And so
as part of its response and you can
actually return both the text and um
these embedded resources and it's up to
the client to figure out what to do. And
so it actually gives you a way to
degrade gracefully. So if you send both
and your client doesn't actually support
MCP UI or the extensions, then it can
just render the text and it never knows
anything about the UI bits. Um or it can
prefer the UI or it can do some
combination of both. Um so they've come
up with the URI schema. Uh they're
picking the UI uh and then giving it a
component name and then some sort of
instance ID.
on the client side. Um there's another
SDK to pick up. It will render those UI
resources looking at the uh URI schema
and validating that. Um and then to
communicate between the um iframe and
the application uh there's a it's just
making use of the post message API uh
the standard one. And so you're able to
out of the box they've got some actions
that are predefined. Uh so the intent is
you know the user wants to do this or
add this to uh cart. Um it can notify it
can uh just submit a prompt on behalf of
the user. Um it can make a direct tool
call. um and then supporting uh links
out of the uh iframe into the system.
So they've done a pretty good job with
this and so we'll see this in action,
but I wanted to give everyone a quick
overview of kind of the components that
excuse me uh that we'll be leveraging.
Any questions?
Cool.
So here we will start with um adding
basic UI elements to this. We're going
to just return uh simple HTML raw. Um
we'll do just the the basics of what we
would want to see. The our first pass
will just be sort of the HTML element.
Uh we're not going to do the interactive
just yet. We'll add that next. Um
so here we're going to add our UI
resource after importing the
um
bring in the MCP UI bits.
So really here the piece that we're
going to be changing is our return. So
we're going to instead of just returning
the
uh text piece of it, we are also going
to return the UI element.
So here we're going to create a UI
resource.
Get text type
and
our content. And
stop it.
Our content is going to be type
raw HTML
and the HTML is going to be
I'm just going to dump the ASKI into a
pre-formatted HTML text block
and
Then we're going to do UI metadata
and we're going to say that we want to
prefer an I frame size.
So yeah, here we're creating our
resource. We've added the new type.
We're going to give it the URI that it
is a board. Um, we're going to encode it
in text. We're just going to dump the
ASKI straight out to a pre-formatted
block. And then here in this UI
metadata,
we're telling the client library that's
going to render this that we would
prefer the iframe to be 700 by 700
pixels.
So, we'll fire that back up.
fire back up our Nanobot server,
start a new thread,
and now move E4.
So now it'll actually render this
pre-formatted ASKI board game every
time. And so
here if we inspect
you'll see that we're in the pre-tags
and that the client has done the iframe
for us and so
it is drawing and rendering this for us
and the client is picking this. Not
every client supports these UI
extensions. Um, but the ones that do,
uh, you can take advantage of this.
Was everyone able to
get the pre-formatted HTML?
Cool.
So again, the key thing here is that we
are returning both types. the text and
the UI element. And so it's up to the
client to decide what to display. Um,
and it still gives us portability. Our
MCP server would still work with a
client that does not support the UI bits
because it would just degrade and use
the text bits.
But now we can move on to the fun side
with the chessboard and actually be able
to drag and drop the chest pieces
and build that. So here we're going to
pull in uh a library that gives you a
graphical chessboard and we will then be
able to move the pieces around um and
then be able to Yeah. And we're going to
be using chessboard.js for this
visualization.
So we will now create a new function in
our MCP server.
So
this will uh get the game UI. So I'll
going to copy it because it's a bit
lengthy.
But I will walk through it. So here what
we're doing [sighs] is again we're
create we created a function that'll
generate the uh create UI resource bit
for us. And so here we're doing another
preferred we're setting our metadata.
We're giving it a a UI element. Um and
this time we're going to go with a 500
by 500. We are encoding it as text and
we're sticking with the raw HTML. Um, if
you wanted to get more fancy, you could
put a templating system in your MCP
server, read render templates, and put
that back out um as raw text or as raw
HTML if you want. Um, so you get the
ability to build really complex
applications with MCP servers.
And so here we're bringing in some
stylesheets that basically just kind of
make it pretty. Um, we have the
chessboard and we're calling the piece
themes and just rendering this board
element and then putting it into the the
body.
So now we'll update our return
content bit. So instead of returning it
all here,
we will
just return we'll call the method and
return that element as well. So we're
still doing the same thing we were
previously which is that we are
returning the text and a graphical
element.
And so now we reload our MCP server
and we
fire up Nanobot.
I say E4.
I now get an actual chessboard. And now
this is much much better because now let
me tell it to go ahead and move.
That's less fun.
So here you're able to make these moves
and then I can say you go back and forth
and you're able to start interacting
with and now you're actually playing
chess with the model.
Oops.
It's not very good with error correction
but or if you make an error to fix it.
But here the key thing is is now this is
a much better way more fun way to
interact and play chess with your agents
um than it is to type the notation each
time.
And so if you want to see
was everyone able to see their
chessboard?
Cool.
So [clears throat]
yeah.
So we're still calling the tool active
tool hand the chest move tool that we
built earlier. Um the UI is making use
of the um the handler which handles the
drag and drop messages which then posts
the message back to the nanomot window
letting it know that it should invoke
the chess move tool. Um, and then the UI
updates the the board.
And so
now you basically have a fully
functioning way to play chess. Um, if
you wanted to enhance this, you can add
additional tools which would get valid
moves or undo a move, which would be
nice to have. Um, get the history of the
game, uh, analyze its positions.
mentioned we're roughly an hour in. So
maybe if you do like five minutes of
questions then you continue break a
little bit.
>> Okay.
>> Would that work?
>> I mean yeah
>> whenever
>> I mean we're Yeah, we're pretty actually
we're further ahead than I thought we
would be with the last one.
>> Yeah.
Um yeah, but any questions? Um
about what we've been doing or what we
can use here.
We used basically a file-based storage.
You could enhance this. You could use a
database and actually store this. Um,
you know, you could add O to it and then
actually host this and then have a way
to actually play uh chess against, you
know, agents and have people connect to
it.
Um, you can have better UI elements. So
you could show all the pieces that were
uh taken off the board or um
you know anything that wasn't um yep
basically any potential next moves you
can just continue to enhance um
and uh show different things.
So yeah, um if you'd like the
root of this outside of the workshop
directory is the complete
implementation. You can see that that
one
has everything implemented and is pretty
cool.
So we can run nanobot.
So here now let's play a game of chess.
And now it has all of the tools. So this
is a bit more fullfeatured than what you
would expect. So here, if I move the
pieces, the agent knows to automatically
move again. The board updates and
refreshes. You know, here we can see
that as you're moving, it's going back
and forth and able to play. I've yet to
actually beat GBT41. Um, but hopefully
someone can. Uh, I guess it cheats, but
yeah.
So, we actually went by pretty quick.
Um, I'm going to be here, um, yeah, for
the rest of this time. And I'm happy to
help anyone or troubleshoot any issues.
I know we ran into a few. Um,
I did want to say if you would, thank
you for staying. And if you would like
to have a chance at winning a $100 Visa
gift card, um, please feel free to
enter. Uh, you can come by our booth
tomorrow. um to claim the prize. And we
will also be raffling off a Nintendo
Switch 2 uh which you can enter at the
table tomorrow. Um but yes, if you do
have any questions or if there's
anything I can help with uh trying to
get through I know there were a few
issues, but happy to walk through those
with you.
>> Thank you, Bill. Thanks for uh you know
spreading your wisdom on MCP amps pui or
bot like so many stuff for people to try
and play with. So I hope you enjoy
enjoyed the session like you said he'll
talk more tomorrow and at the booth uh
you can find them. Um do give speakers
feedback right this is important for us
and the speakers as uh we know whether
you liked it or not and what they can
improve. It's always hard to get
feedback right Bill?
>> It is.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
So, uh, and I think you're off now for,
you know, a break a little bit faster
than expected. Uh, so you can get
probably some food or wander around, uh,
the campus. Um, and yeah, I think that's
it from me. So, don't forget the survey
and we're going to start again for the
last workshop. Uh, I hope you enjoyed it
as much as this one. Thank you very
much, Bill.
>> Thank you, Andrew.
[applause]
>> [music]